Guide to the William Procter Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Procter papers
1920-1938
MS 1049
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Chiefly William Procter's records of laboratory and field observations of invertebrates, principally protozoa and various worms, with a notebook of mounted drawings of protozoa. Letters, newspapers clippings on non-scientific matters, and several poems are also in the papers.
Procter, William, 1872-1951
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Procter, 1951.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers of William Procter consist for the most part of records of laboratory and field observations of invertebrates, principally protozoa and various worms. Included is a notebook of mounted drawings of protozoa. There are also two letters in the collection, both from scholars, and an assortment of newspaper clippings on national financial matters and other non-scientific matters, as well as several copies of poems.
These papers were given to Yale University by William Procter in 1951.
Biographical / Historical
William Procter, Ph.B. 1894. Born September 8, 1872, Cincinnati, Ohio; died April 19, 1951, West Palm Beach, Fla.
Father, Harley Thomas Procter, partner Procter & Gamble Company, Cincinnati; son of William Procter. Mother, Mary Elizabeth (Sanford) Procter; daughter of Aaron and Flora Jane (Beardsley) Sanford. Yale relatives include: Thomas Tousey (B.A. 1707) (great-great-great-great-grandfather); William H. Sanford, '84 (uncle).
Phillips-Exeter. Member The Colony and Berzelius.
Student The Sorbonne 1896-97; with Redmond, Kerr & Company, bankers, 1898 and Kountze Brothers 1898-1901; organizer and partner Procter & Borden, bonds, New York City, 1902-20; graduate student Columbia 1917-20; established laboratory on Mount Desert Island, Maine, 1921, and in 1926 established Biological Survey of the Mount Desert Region (president 1926-51); an authority on marine and insect life of the Region (author of many publications and contributed to curricula of universities and State biological departments); research associate in marine biology Academy of Natural Sciences, Philadelphia; Sc.D. Montreal 1935; member advisory board zoology department Columbia 1942-47; president Bar Harbor Hospital 1923-30; member board Wistar Institute of Anatomy and Biology 1917-20, 1928-40; trustee American Museum of Natural History; a founder and governor Scientific Research Society of America; member Sigma Xi, Boston Society of Natural History, Academy of Natural Sciences, New York Academy of Science, American Association for the Advancement of Science, American Microscopical Society, Ornithologists' Union, Genetic Society, New York, Brooklyn and Cambridge Entomological societies, Ray Society of London, Plymouth Marine Association, Ecologists Union, Ecological Society of America, Royal Canadian Institute; warden Bethesda-by-the-Sea Church (Episcopal), Palm Beach.
Married February 3, 1910, New York City, Emily Pearson, daughter of Frederick W. and Julia (Northhall) Bodstein. Mrs. Procter died 1949.
Death due to heart attack. Buried in Bar Harbor (Maine) Cemetery. Survived by a brother, Rodney Procter, '03 S.
(Taken from Yale University Obituary Record, Sheffield Scientific School, 1949-51, pp. 105-106).
Biology; Protozoa; Science; Worms; Mount Desert Island (Me.); Biologists; Procter, William, 1872-1951
- Inventory
  - Scientific papers
    - Drawings of protozoa, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Key to microscope slides of Lophius veil, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notes on annelids, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Directions for Dissection of Arenicola", undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Key to the Eggs of Ithaca Anura", undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Notes on nemerteans, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Checklist of ocean organisms, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters
    - Kirtland, John C., 1932 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Marie-Victorin, Frère, 1937 January 28
  - Newspaper clippings on financial and other non-scientific subjects, 1928-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Poems, 1920, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)